okay yeah it's I think the gradual
moving into and realization of these
different modes of dialogue is something
that's very very interesting and I know
something that is fascinating you at the
moment and I see it at tying in deeply
to the series awakening from the meaning
crisis and particularly of course the
sort of response aspect of how we come
to terms with and ultimately move
through ameliorate as you put it that
perennial problems we face mm-hmm and I
log is one of many modes of expression
experience response that we might take
to these perennial problems and and I
was trying to trying to fill back in and
sort of drop in to where where we are
now yeah I've been engaging we do a
series a lot to the last few days and
thank you yeah I've actually been
listening to you on occasion
double-time so I'm hoping that this
conversation will be a little bit easier
for you to follow along it's funny when
you lose but you flip back from double
time to single it like whoo oh it feels
so slow for a few seconds yeah yeah okay
but it's the double time was was
literally just to get through some
things I thought I need to make sure
that there are key pieces I'm missing
out on here before we saw a speak mmm
and I definitely prefer that the single
time version of it and you know Jonas
it's um it's a challenging thing and
this might bring us to a point of sort
of articulating some of the productive
nature of dialogue but also the
conditions which sort of have to be
present to engage in it because what I'm
feeling right now just to speak on my
state
is a mixture of extreme gratitude for
the opportunity to dialogue with you I'm
also feeling the tremendous breadth of
the whole series and an interest to
speak to that dynamic and context so
that we've got as much as we possibly
can have on the table between us so that
we can in some sense both together
orient towards what might be of sort of
mutual interest to explore and so much
of what you explore I find deeply
important and and crucial for me
personally to gain further insight and
familiarity with so that I can in
collaboration with others build the
kinds of communities and ultimately
experiences that facilitate some of this
deep development that is part and parcel
of meeting and responding to the meaning
crisis and so there's all of this
breadth and then there's at the same
time when it comes to dialogue a certain
sense of a certain sense of safety and
smoothness and being just where we are
and and so in some meta way I this is me
I'm suppose expressing to you a little
bit of where I am which is gradually
feeling into a way in here and so if I
draw into a question
hmm
where do you feel this notion of
dialogue
it's a Socratic dialogue but there's
also I sense a bit more of an intimacy
to what you're exploring could you uh
could you articulate how that is alive
for you at the moment and how you feel
that this may be an important practice
to situate within our ecology of ways we
can develop and ameliorate and move
through some of the perennial problems
we face as existential beings oh great I
think that's an excellent question
before I address the question I first
want to respond
I really appreciated your careful I mean
that in a very positive sense you're
very careful articulation of how you're
framing the framing you're bringing to
bear into this interaction I thought
that was a very very helpful thing for
me and I think also very very helpful
for potential listeners so I just wanted
to say thank you for doing that I think
taking the time that's in my mind that's
analogous to the importance they give to
problem formulation it's kind of like
dialogue formulation how are we
formulating the dialogue before we
immediately leap in and try to solve or
resolve or whatever we're gonna do in
the dialogue spending that time to first
formulate the dialogue explicate it make
sure that we share we have a shared
commitment to this formulation so I
think that right but I think that's an
exemplary thing you just did so I want
to commend you on that I want to express
my appreciation for that in both senses
of the word like the gratitude and the
understanding for why you did that so
thank you very much for that and that of
course is a nice segue into your
question the question that you're
actually posed to me huh so a bit of the
genealogy of how it emerged and and it
will give me a way of getting a little
bit better where it's at
so I've been I mean in conjunction with
the awakening from the meaning crisis of
course I've been talking a lot about
this need for an ecology practice
ecology practices you know setting up
counterbalancing self-organizing systems
of cyclic tech in order to as you say
ameliorate the printing of problems and
perhaps also enhance and afford
increased sense of senses of connection
to himself to other people to the world
all of that and I was in I wanted a
partial another motive for this is also
give appropriate credit and it and it's
not just a moral thing I'm doing I'm
trying to also show the role the vital
role of distributed cognition in the
work we're doing that often gets masked
by kind of individualistic ideology that
I want to challenge not only what I'm
saying but in what I'm exemplifying so I
was in one of these kinds of discussions
with somebody who I've who's I've come
to have a lot of affection for deep
appreciation for Jordan Hall Jordan is
especially important for the manner in
which he converses I'm not saying he
doesn't have great ideas he does he has
great insights but people tend to focus
a little too rapidly on content and not
pay enough attention to the way he's
doing all this really important work
again around the manner and the
formulation of the dialogue so I was in
discussion with him and I was trying to
get out of his notion of coherence we're
comparing it yeah and he had this
insight he said well what I think I'm
pointing towards is the need for a meta
psychic technology whose role it is is
to help generate curate and organize the
the the ecology of cyclic technology so
I used this sort of metaphor of
shepherding we need something that
Shepherds it and I thought and I think
that just struck me as oh wow that's a
that's sort of that's a brilliant
insight and it was in my mind there's a
relationship between our individuals
cultivate wisdom and you know and then
write that this needed Metta psycho
technology so then I got thinking and
then I realized that the ancient world
had something deeply analogous to this
which was
the practice of dialectic which came out
of Socratic and Linkous and it ramifies
through Plato
and then it goes in all kinds of
important directions in them Neoplatonic
a tradition now the thing about
dialectic and if you read the
neoplatonist it's very clear that it had
this status of being a meta psychic
technology it is sort of the meta
practice you do so you know how to best
do the other practices and curate and
coordinate them together and the
interesting thing about the dialectic is
it's it's both something you do as an
individual sort of ontological II and
then something you do with other people
discursive ly and that these are these
two dimensions are integrated in a
powerful way so well all I was saying oh
well I should I should better understand
that because that would serve as a
valuable template for trying to
understand what what Jordan was talking
about and then and and it was of course
deeply enmeshed with the wisdom project
which was the connection I was seeking
so then I thought oh that's really
interesting because that also ties in
with this stuff that's also been
happening you can see it up for example
on rebel wisdom about the rediscovery of
the power of the collective intelligence
that is generated by distributed
cognition and you know there's now some
you know even some hard science a little
bit some of its ghastly about the power
of distributed cognition like they
directly linked to brain a rat brains
together and and and that collectivity
can solve problems that individual rats
can't solve with the computational power
right right and then there's all the
stuff about the brain synchrony between
human beings I won't get into the nuts
and bolts of it so there's all this
emerging stuff and then I thought oh and
then I and then I got to meet somebody
else who I'm forming a very deep
friendship with you just talked to him
guys in stock and you know at the so
there's all these emerging psycho
technologies and especially guys
circling because guys circling is so
impregnated with the wisdom project of
Heidi garyun and existential philosophy
that it's it's exactly the kind of thing
right I'm talking about as something
that has analogous elements with ancient
dialectic so I've been I've been
engaging with the help of peter
lindbergh and the wonderful people in in
my circling group so I'm doing
participant
observation learning some of these other
discourse modalities did some empathy
circling recently uploaded that video
doing some insight gonna do some inside
dialogue
anyways learning all of these things and
so it struck me that dialectic was also
the machinery in the ancient world by
which people were tailoring themselves
to and entering into right the
collective intelligence of distributed
cognition and they often spoke of this
in religious terms what's really
interesting to me that when I'm in the
circling practice for example is how
spontaneously people often from very
secular orientation will will thought
will find themselves using very
spiritual even religious terms to talk
about the phenomenology and the change
and functionality that's occurring in
these practices so I just saw that as a
massive convergence I saw okay here's
all this stuff going on about the
collective intelligence and distributed
cognition
here's ancient dialectic and there's all
these new and wonderful texts being
generated around this like sera sera a
rapid book on Socrates for example is
just amazing and they're right and
there's that the coordination with
Jordans idea about the meta psychic
technology and and then they're like I
said it struck me that well what we
could do is we could and that's what I'm
gonna do in the next series we could
explore right now all these current
emerging biological practices put that
into dialogue and I don't mean that as a
pun I mean that as a real thing put that
into dialogue with what I can get what
if I could get glean from an garner for
the practice of ancient dialectic and
see if we can then bring you know some
elucidation some clarification some
insight some advancement of the project
because here's here's that here's the
key idea just like individual
intelligence needs to be exhausted up
into rationality and then that exact
that up into wisdom we need to take
collective intelligence and ratchet that
out into collective rationality and in
connective wisdom collective wisdom and
those two projects are deeply
interpenetrating and so that's what I
think we need in order to get to you the
meta secular technology so I'm doing a
lot of work
with Christopher master Pietro by the
way you should have him on your you
should have Yujin interview Chris right
I so Chris and I are writing a chapter
for the meta modern anthology on just
the stuff you were talking about it's
also going into the the book we're
working on so there so I'm doing a lot
of work with Chris right now to try and
nail down some of the theory and doing a
lot of work with Peter on the imputed
Limburg investing investigating it with
to this participant observation reading
the literature together so there's a lot
of people we're all working together
some of them I get to work with directly
in collaboration some of it's more of a
network that I'm contributing to to try
and I think get this I know that guy for
example is extremely excited he texted
me the other day he said he wanted to he
want he's really excited to do circling
2.0 because he wants to try and
incorporate all of this stuff in into
circling that I'm talking to you about
so that's that's why I'm sort of getting
very excited right now because there's a
lot of excitement I think there's a lot
of I think there's a lot of real
potential here to to create to cultivate
to help in advance this kind of meta
psycho technology and access ultimately
collective rationality and collective
wisdom so that we have something that
can really vet our attempts to create
the ecology of practices that are needed
to address and ameliorate the meeting
crisis so that's sort of a gist of and
and I asked for forbearance from all
your listeners and your viewers because
this is very much a work in progress
this is something I'm you know I'm doing
work on now trying to get the
phenomenology and the functionality of
all of this worked out but this is where
this is where it's at like yeah oh yeah
beautiful John thank you so much for
that answer that was that was that was
excellent
it's very exciting I feel that same
sense of of interest and excitement
about it and will continue to be
gathering with people here both in
person online and then around the world
in person eventually when I get off and
away from here for just a little bit to
be doing exactly that it's some attempt
to move into insight practice in a co
participatory way this this is this
movement towards presencing wisdom about
that ultimately in which in some sense
we are already bringing to bear and
presencing in our own lives to get by in
the world this set of psycho
technologies that are already in play
the ones that are already emerging so is
it a fair formulation to think about a
meta psycho technology as the continual
renewal or establishment and renewal of
Co participatory wisdom oh I think
that's an excellent way of putting it I
think it's it's it's participatory in
both if you'll allow me the metaphor is
horizontal between people and vertical
within a person because there's a sense
if with if this if this machinery isn't
already to some degree active in you you
need it to start to get into it it's
like a virtue
if you it's like you need you're right
you need a bit of honesty to cultivate
more of honesty and that's sort of thing
you need that germinating spark kind of
idea so I think you all altima lyon lee
know this kind of wisdom by
participating in it and then like you
said it's very much also and this is
what this is what has such some of the
most powerful phenomenological effects
on people that sense of that's why it's
often called the Wiis face the
participation in some right some
emerging emergent thing emergent
presence I've got to be careful where
with my language because I don't want to
invoke you know weird a weird
metaphysics but you get this you get
this we face that is not reducible to
any one particular individual cognition
and so and your relationship to it one
is one a participation it's not other
than you but it's not identical to you
you participate in it and and it's I
didn't mean and again that's why it
harkens back to you know sort of
theoretic language it's I mean and it
even survives in some of her metaphors
we talk about team spirit well at one
point that was really a phenomenological
thing it wasn't just sort of Yoho right
it was us and right so when you're when
you're doing something like circling you
yeah you get that but it's not just a
metaphor for our shared commitment it's
the extent aesthetic experience of you
know of the dynamical system that has
taken shape between all the people
involved and and that and sort of the
power it has to alter and shift
individual cognition so yeah I think
that that that it's a it's deeply
participatory in both with Ian you you
have to read you like you have to be it
you can't just think about it you have
to embody it and then it's also deeply
participatory in that you have this
relationship to the we space all right
the that is again it's not it's not
other and it's not me it's not I it's
it's we so it's deeply it's it's
phenomenology is inherently
participatory in nature mmm-hmm and then
as you said what that's all directed
towards and what I want to even more
directed towards with the help of people
like Jordan and guy and Chris is as you
said towards the individual and
collective cultivation of wisdom so
that's why there's the subtitle so
there's the next series is after
Socrates the pursuit of wisdom through
authentic dialogue mmm-hmm yeah
yeah that's that battle seems right to
me
so I wonder if this is an interesting
way in because okay okay so so in one
sense it seems like where we are to go
in dialogue which neither of us know
right now is in some sense is substance
emergent and in another sense its latent
already in each of us individually our
current maps of making sense of things
and also our orientation and way we are
willing to be that and show up and
embody that and to be continuous between
that proposition and participatory level
when to the extent we can generate the
perspective of knowing so we can both
participate in that to the extent I have
the words right in to procedurally be
able to do that as well we are we are
here at this opening and I'd like to I'd
like to present a little bit about where
I feel myself ultimately going and that
doesn't mean we have to go there right
now there's this there's this balance
sighs there's this balance that's
important to hold isn't it between the
being well being where we are and being
and ultimately actually my my
fundamental goal here is to be helpful
in a collaborative way towards that very
project and and I would actually love to
talk to you about how that project
relates to a lot of how I am driven to
show up in the world and broadly
speaking these collaborations toward the
creation of communities that enable
wisdom enable the development of psycho
technologies the practicing of different
psycho technologies
based on the sovereign choice of
individuals to move towards that in
their life and to realize a deeper
connection to themselves each other and
the world well we also make sense of
where we're at in our collective moment
for me this is absolutely essential and
serving that is what my primary aim is
yet that is if that is something that's
it's a live project and
we have the moment of this conversation
I have my individual places of where I'm
at with considering for example some of
the deeper metaphysical aspects to your
theorizing because your theorizing has
been so important to me you're a key
influencer of mine because of me for
many beautiful ways it's we don't have
time to talk about it precisely today
and so there's all of these aspects of
myself that in some sense are desiring
to presents themselves yet there is a
thread that if I tend to it is also one
that can be between us that is mutually
interesting and revelatory for both of
us
I think what you're doing right now is
already extremely helpful so the
interesting one of the interesting
dimensions that I call it the theory a
theory dimension so one of the things
we're doing in this practice is we're
constantly moving right and it's it's a
matter of the way in which attention and
perspectival knowing or shifting right
but we're constantly moving between
theory in which we advance propositional
arguments right and then but then then
we do what you just did we step back
into the-- Oriya which is we step back
into a contemplative frame in which
we're again ok where are we what's the
agent arena you know set up here how are
we formulating the dialogue and then
what we're doing there is we're trying
to come alive - we're trying to increase
our sensitivity and transform our
Sensibility so we can sense the Kairos
so we can sense like the way in which
this is shifting and directing and
there's so much finesse here if there's
about it almost like there's no
musicality and you're trying to get the
rhythm you're trying to sense the tone
and so you have to you have to
consciously shift into the OREA - sense
and also your but it's it's not just a
sensing thing there's an aspiration
thing you're also you're also training
your sensibility like music appreciation
so you're doing this sensing and
transforming your sensibility to pick up
on the musicality of the dialogue so
that when you come back in it's not just
you and the other person both of you
like are sharing this commitment to
what's emerging between you so first of
all I think what you just did about
right and and so
I think this is a vital and I'm using
that word to try and resonate with as
many meanings impossible with it I think
what you just did is a vital thing that
that theory theory a shift and I was
talking to Jordan about this I would see
and and and about how it's about
sensitizing but also transforming
sensibility to pick up on the musicality
I think that that's just like I think
that's actually vital to what we're
trying to do here right now and it's
important therefore it for people who
are interested in what we're talking
about to pay attention to this
exemplification and not just the the
explicit content of our propositions so
I think that that was a bit that was a
very that that for me that see that's
the kind of thing I'm interested in
right now I'm trying to get at like
what's in practice what's the
transformations of the phenomenology
that tell us something about how to
access and transform the funk underlying
functionality and and so just here just
now you doing that in fact that you did
it so spontaneously and so well is it
exact exactly the kind of thing that I'm
very interested in and and I think is as
I say vital to trying to to get this the
idea and even the metaphor you had of
the thread is so good because right
there's a sense in which you know you
have you have to you to really play with
salience to in the midst of all the
other things to find the thread and and
then there's a kind of diligence and a
respect that you have to set yourself
into to to follow the thread so yes I
think all of that is important and
here's another word I want to use with
as much resonance as possible it's
important to invoke all of this on a
regular and reliable basis rather than
simply referring to it hmm
yes yes yes there's a sense in which
so I'm let me see if I can use the term
furia here a little bit in practice so
that I can further get it it's not every
day that conversations are available to
use the word theoria in okay so well so
this is a different way in there's a
there's a movement towards an to write
an unscripted mode because there is this
necessity
I feel the language is appropriate I
feel to to presence actually and gently
as we have almost an opponent processing
towards it yes we have an opponent
processing towards the appropriate place
of vulnerability and that vulnerability
is more but the vulnerabilities involved
and that vulnerability from me in this
moment
especially when we are skimming along
the surface of what our deep
metaphysical cogs and highly direct
ontology and epistemology is these are
the kinds of vulnerabilities that can in
fact as you speak about so interesting
me in one of your lecture episodes
invoke a sense of horror if they are yep
miss play or if they are dislodged
without the right bounds of safety and
I'm very attuned to this and I and I
actually have considerable experience in
deep metaphysical unsettling and
epistemological and ontological
unsettling over the course of many years
and in that sense I feel ready to be
here and do this but there's a sense in
which when I'm talking about this stuff
I I realize how effectively Laden I am
- presents my words and it's the
affective component that you also speak
about an awful lot as being a key
characterization of how we should
understand relevance realization oh
totally I mean it's the the coping of
relevance realization is in separately
bound up with a primordial kind of
caring yes beautiful carrot it's it's
precisely that and for me I was using
the language of an affective relation
before I became so acquainted with your
work to express to myself that there was
some important contrast between an
intellectual way of going at the world
and that in some sense our frames were
always and already filtered to some
degree by something like and you know I
was influenced a lot by your thinking
before I came to study you a lot because
I had engaged with it a little bit and
the time breath at the time relevance
realization is itself it reveals you
know the more the more you understand of
it the more you can drop the whole just
through appreciating the terms I think
it's very very appropriate it's a very
very true thing the right terms is a
very important thing to do oh yeah yeah
and you know and that's something
actually that I think can be afforded
like the dialogue can help I think
spontaneously to generate those terms
but it could also be not precisely the
place where you look for them and I know
this in my own experience because so
often I'm looking to communicate that
affective component to to enable this
sense of shared safety and care so I
will go about expressing things in all
these different ways coming out of this
like this like this with these different
emotional tones behind it but that's not
kind of I would sit down to write
something if I wanted to make something
analytically tight in the way that
relevance realization has to be
analytically tight for it to play that
role between the cognitive science on
the one hand and then also the religion
yeah so yeah I I think I wanted it to be
because you made it a couple of really
excellent points I did I didn't want I
didn't want them to to be left one look
at the thing you just said I think
there's yeah I think and and there's a
big difference between theorizing which
I think we need to do and there
you need those precise terms and you
shouldn't produce until you've come to
precision yes I agree with that and that
is the appropriate place to do that but
I think to go back to two points you
made about dia logos and I try to use
the Greek now by way of the logos
because their logos right is much more
comprehensive than logic right it's it's
the gathering together so that things
belong together so but India logos
there's two things you said that are
very important first we're putting
ourselves on the edge of we're putting
yourself into a system that's dynamical
and and that is going to have emergent
features the the ongoing emergence of
what we have not pre-planned or
prepackaged or pre cognized pre thought
right is is again a vital piece of it
next you mentioned about the effectivity
and you mentioned the vulnerability and
there's a way in which I'm sort of
seeing these coming together because I
was really I I really liked what you
when you and I were talking about for
the distinction between ball in the bill
and exposure that had come up guy and I
talked a bit about that and then I think
he talked to her at length with Jordan
about that because it's it's this notion
again of sensitization right the
difference when you're exposed right
what did you actually what the response
is to is it is a hardening right the
response is a hardening and because what
you're trying to do is defend and
protect yourself from further incursion
but in vulnerability if we're using it
as distinct from exposure because of
course people use terms in all kinds of
sloppy ways but if we're using it in in
the distinction vulnerability is a kind
of sensitization you're allowing
yourself to the things to penetrate into
you so it comes with that sensitivity
and I think that's exactly where the
affective component has to be our guide
because what our effect is often doing
is giving us the degree to which our our
ability to perceive and sense is is is
threatening or the degree to which it's
nourishing our effect is often you know
deeply attuned to okay what it what it
what is this doing and so I think being
able to
you know courage and care with
vulnerability is what affords it to be
actually become that sensitivity and so
a lot of what we are doing is and again
to try and you know really make this
word resonate with people we're trying
to encourage each other and if you'll
allow me to coin a new word we're trying
to in care each other we're trying to
create right caring between and within
each other so that we can that the
vulnerability stays at become it stays
as a sensitivity it doesn't harden into
a defensive framing of I'm overexposed
and then that that in turn you know
leads me back to the point you made
about and this is this is one I hope we
can spend some time on because it's it's
it's kind of that the the the the the
tangled but really juicy part if I can
put it that way which is we need we're
not we need a place for theorizing let's
put that aside I've already acknowledged
that and I do that and that's important
and people know that I care about that
so I'm gonna take it that that's a given
that we need nothing that we're doing
here challenges any of that or
undermines it in any way but when we're
doing deal logos right we do need to
bring into it the depths of our ontology
and you'll allow me we have this is what
this is what I see exemplified in Plato
right you can't if you really want to
cultivate wisdom and courage and virtue
these are deeply perspectival
participatory things and therefore your
deepest patterns of intelligibility your
deepest patterns of coping and
sense-making are always bound up with
your deepest patterns of caring and
concern and identification and so I mean
if we want this to have existential
depth we have to touch upon the you know
the the ontological depths as well and
so how to do this and you can see that
this is a vital issue in Plato they talk
about it in the dialogue how to do this
you want to be able to take people even
to up
aurilla where they're like ah it doesn't
make sense anymore but but not tip them
into as you said horror because the the
point isn't to the is is it to
immobilize people because they've now
overexposed and they hardened another
stock what you want to do is you want to
take that and get them to commit to it
so that that becomes Wonder and awe and
it draws them forth in an aspirational
commitment and so that is also part of
the finesse of the the via logos and so
I often describe this to Gaia's I want
to take circling but I want to bring
find Leah Sophia into it and I want to
bring in right so we're doing all the
stuff all this really valuable and rich
and juicy stuff we're circling but we
but if we get aware of all of these
dimensions can we then bring them in can
we then bring in finally by the assaut
fiha because the deepest and the I mean
guy is all on board about this because
this is heidegger's whole thing right
you can't actually explore design
without exploring being those two are
bound together in just inseparable
fashion and so um III that's why I
wanted to interrupt you there was like
four really important things you had you
had you had canvassed there and I
thought they were important to slow down
and open them up and unpack them a
little bit yes thank you for doing that
I thought that was beautiful I'm packing
and I continue to invite you to slow me
down and do just that and and in many
respects the point I was making was one
that was inviting you to jump in and
slow it slow it down because there's so
much and it needs to be there's this
time and care to be taken in presencing
that and also we're recording something
for the benefit of listeners and viewers
as well so there's all these pieces and
and my sense as well as that so the
sorts of meta reflection which not that
theory is precise
I mean it's it's a reflection of a kind
it's but not so much an intellectual and
as it is this bearing forth of where we
are and our being in the moment which
can look
like a type of sort of meta taking once
out oneself out of the particular frame
there's there's a there's a deeper well
that is that is a process that should be
gentle that is that is a process that
should be gentle and and and I'd like to
I'd like to continue it so okay so we're
may be interesting to explore is where
the perhaps where the jump back into
theorizing takes place within the space
of Peoria within the space of this
presencing our being this effectively
cooperatively realizing a shared space
of care and vulnerability so that we can
presence truly what we are as much as we
can reveal of ourselves in accordance
with what we can in an integrated
fashion and respectful fashion be
together in a space as appropriate to
the setting and the setting isn't is it
important it's like not only are we
doing this thing we're also building the
table this is often what I'm talking to
people about it's like not only not only
are we present seeing sort of ourselves
in this dance at the same time there's a
construction of the table at which this
kind of conversation can take place of
course you're a motorway for so much of
your life but with this with this online
element right and with this with that
with what seems to me that the genuine
novelty of this just because of how
actually of how existentially demanding
I truly feel it is to to move at this
level right there is you know I come at
this a lot as well from a perspective of
therapy and what education
Kumiko so let's let's press ahead and
trust the trust the process anyway it's
it's really part and parcel of exactly
what we're talking about because you
know it's this constant dynamic of
feeling you know of the desire to
participate and then also accepting
precisely where you are and not going to
further than it's just breaching the
boundary yeah and this is a big part of
my my day to day kind of process but
where I believe I was at just to pick
things up for our audiences presencing
also this therapeutic aspect and the
conditions which enable in fact trauma
to be moved through and positively
developed or growth to occur from this
state there's a sense in which we want
to avoid that which we want to avoid
presencing that which locks us and
freezes us and stops us from being able
to be in a productive relationship with
it and so yes there's a deep importance
to the tenderly establishing this domain
of shared care and where I was moving
potentially in the his where I can pose
a question is so we we see Oriya is in
aiding us to presence the the being and
the depths of our ontology creating a
landscape of care in which that can be
done and then also also now we might
consider how we move back into the
theory and I wonder how you'd
characterize that tone so that's
excellent and and that's that I mean and
the thing of it is again we've got the
germ of it because we've been doing it
and we keep cycling here and so it's not
a matter of creating something to know
who it's a matter of trying to vary
through participant observation trying
to sort of delicately extricate into
sort of stable theory theoretical terms
and formulation what is what it is
that's going on here and so
there there seems to be some aspects
here the turn back to theory is the kind
uh the kind of thing I see going on
again in the Platonic dialogue in which
you are not
there's never there's that there's never
Manav logic argumentation there's
argumentation but it's always bound up
with questioning because you're always
seeking to involve the other and there's
as much a again a a receptivity for a
seeking of insight as there is the
attempt to you know come to some sort of
argumentative conclusion so well well
there should be Theory the theory going
on and theorizing I don't it III I sound
like I'm splitting hairs but I'm trying
to be very very careful here well there
should be theorizing going on I don't
think there should be Theory building
going on which is it which is a
different thing right so one of the I
mean again again I'm asking for
everybody's patience I'm trying to this
is very much work in progress
but you know what thira we keep
theorizing we step back and we do the
theory we weary presence ourself we
restructure the salience the landscape
we reinvestigate we sensitize we're
doing all that stuff right and then but
then we also do this we we bring we and
this is where guys invoke implication of
this phrase I think is so pregnant we
come to terms we come to terms about
what's happening there we we try to it's
almost like poesis we try to put it into
terms and then and then and then we and
then we question each other we challenge
each other we we link things together
but the inference is always open to
being impregnated and redirected by the
insight and the insight is always open
to being challenged and right and we
structured again by the inference and
we're trying to get it's very much like
when I go there stuff I talk about you
know and how in rationality we're trying
to balance insight and inference and
internalization off against each other
that's why I think it's you can't really
come into these practices in any depth
if you are if you haven't already
started down a sappy antral pathway
where you've got some ecologies you've
got some individual practices for
insight and inference and
zatia and you've got some a basic
ecology for for for networking them
together because I I think that's what
you're trying to do in theorizing so you
see rising is yeah yeah I'm bringing up
elements of theory in that there there's
inferential moves being made there's
insight and those are talking to each
other but I don't get into monologue
right the internalization is always
present you are always there you're
always impregnating and I'm using all
these metaphors because those are the
metaphors Socrates is using right and we
still think about the how the word
concept originally goes back to concede
right and being the Midwife so there's
that but we're not trying to - to -
we're trying to stay with Plato and not
get into Aristotle not because Aristotle
doesn't have value but an Aristotle I
don't think it's due to aerosol I think
it's due to an accident of history but
an Aristotle all we have is the
monologic treatise and we want to stay
in the Platonic dialogue elsewhere when
we're doing the science then we do the
Aristotelian thing then we do the theory
building we should theorize there should
be inference and insight and
internalization but we shouldn't do
theory building we should generate lots
of things that we can then look back on
and say right Oh from from within that
participant observation there's all of
these things I could take them out and
do some theory building or I can bring
some theory over here and carve your
science to bear on this and that's why I
think there's kind of a meta dialogue
between what's going on in via logos and
the scientific study of distributed
cognition and collective intelligence so
I don't know that's adequate but I think
it's a good beginning
you know what the turn back to theory is
is that's a that's that's appropriate
and fine to say but keep it distinct
from the the the desire to drop into
monologic theory building that that's
one of the things I would recommend yes
I hear that I hear that ok so here's
something that may open this out in an
interesting way or maybe bring it to a
more fine point so something that has
been a key interest of mine for some
years has been
the the you know a recurse you know
seeking sort of a recursive elegance to
how I express modes of orientation in
particular states of consciousness and
the reason I'm present seeing this is
because also as well I believe what I'm
looking to do when I'm using some terms
to refer to these modes of orientation
in consciousness which may look very
much like particular meditative or
contemplative turns within your own
experience right the mindfulness for
passenger and the contemplation they're
sort of grasping out again of the sort
of paying attention to something beyond
just the well as like it is like the
internal quietening the paying attention
to what sort of flowing through and then
there's also it's moving again towards
me it's slightly more on the side of but
it's certainly more in touch with the
world in a little way at attempting to
feel into a deeper connection with it
and and I'm I mean to speak from a
perspective that's process philosophical
so I'm not looking to stress be from a
perspective where we are sort of
identifying the fix to substances
bashing into each other and certainly
not because ultimately what what I would
like to move towards as well as invoking
a discussion of sacredness and a sacred
in here to because there's a sense in
which sacredness as you articulated in
the series must be seen through a lens
of well of course it's forever
incomplete yet at the same time enabling
of experiences of deep connection and
unity so it's the relevance realization
that never ends it
continued transformation and this is
very much accordant with how it's it's
very well with me it's in my own
theorizing it's a deep constitutive part
of that yet I also feel I'm I'm looking
for and have been looking for some
reliable ways to refer to what is
experienced in cycles of transformation
which are something like waypoints which
could be mistaken for a certain kind of
fixation but they're not a fixation on
the substance side of things it's not a
finality it's not like this is all there
is and the process is complete when we
spoke last time we spoke a little bit
about teleology and I realized that the
way I was using teleology was in a
continual self making sense which is not
semantically how you how we how you were
using that word and I may not be
entitled to use the word teleology
precisely because I'm endorsing a
continued self making right but I'm
endorsing and continued self making in
respect of what enables like what are
the core orientation modes what are the
the fundamental features the almost the
minimal viable necessities for a
successful transformation that enables
further transformation it seems to me
like some houses do end fundamentally
and what we are in the process of
opening and closing as appropriate to
continue transformation and I prefer to
that in my own to my own self as and
people as loving transformation and this
seems appropriate to me and its
relevance realization may in fact just
be that or it might be a key like a very
a deep piece of it and then in a
slightly more and I guess we have this
loving transformation or something like
a self making Tilos in perpetuity but it
also in these notions of Agape in there
and an agog a so it's a loving position
because consider
goal element of relevance realization
which which it needs it's coming it's
like it's like a given Asst that it take
like it takes finds itself interesting
for itself
I say you're loving for itself it's not
just the interest isn't enough isn't
enough for me it's not enough I think it
needs a love okay and in this deep
interconnected way and what we're doing
it when we're caring for each other it's
the agape as you as you express it's
this love and so yes that's quite a lot
of thoughts I know I've jumped a fair
way ahead here but it may be why it was
wonderful though yeah it was real I
really I found out wonderful yeah I
found out wonderful yet there's so much
there yeah it's so so yeah the way you
woke that together it's I didn't want to
interrupt because it was flowing so
smoothly let me try and see if I can
riff on some of the points that sort of
spring to mind
as I review the course of that um so
this lets let's start with the love and
if this brings us back to that notion I
had and you invoked an agape as well as
a drop-by
so I think it's appropriate the dis
notion of mutually reciprocal opening
mutually accelerating disclosure right
and the idea that you know if I
understand vulnerability as a
sensitivity a sensitivity to allowing
not just my mind but my identity to be
restructured not just in a cognitive
insight but in an existential insight
that will call forth that will adduce
right and maybe there's the
vulnerability to the world that will
call for us or reduce from the world it
will disclose itself in ways it couldn't
disclose itself to me before there was a
way in which I was imposing on the world
and now and it would kind of wilt the
power a romantic sense and now if I if I
do that restructuring of my identity
that that allows the world to disclose
itself in a way this is Wright's notion
of the senseability transcendence and
that that and that we experience this is
Aaron's work we experience mutually
accelerating disclosure as love that's
how you fall in love with
somebody or something or someplace
that's how it works because it's it's
that deep that that's the knowing of
yourself and then knowing of whatever it
is you're right you're coupled to are so
into band together that you're the the
the the inherent self loving which isn't
the same thing as selfishness of
relevance realization is bound up with
the relevance realization that is
occurring you know
directed towards the world I think all
of that the way you put that together
yes I understand
also the thinness of the word interest I
tried to use that word and I'm doing
work with John Logan on this trying to
go back to the original meaning of the
word interesa to be within something to
be within something and trying to
revaloris like many of our terms we've
trivialized that we've thinned it out
dude we just must be a simple
referential label and not not something
that sort of more poetically discloses
the depths of something but to be within
interesa that right yeah like so I was I
was trying to play on the idea that
relevance realization is constituted by
its consists within this kind of
relationship to itself if it if it if
it's not self monitoring and self caring
and self coping and self making and self
organizing it's not profoundly
autopoietic in that way it's not going
to be functioning as relevance
realization so I understand what you're
trying to convey with love what I'm
saying is I it was my intent with the
word interest sure that etymological
explorations that deeper meaning and and
therefore give people a term so let me
be careful here give people that term
other than love for trying to talk about
something that grounds what we normally
call love
but now you've you've taken it in
another way you've said no I want to
take the word love and I want to deepen
it down to reach this transformative
death I think those two things are
actually converging I think those two
points are actually deeply convergent
and then that brings me into the other
thing that and here's in theorizing we
want to talk about it we want to do
conceptual analysis on it but in theory
oh we're trying to invoke it we're
you saying we're trying to presents it
and we're trying to give it a like we're
trying to give it a functional role
right a place in a deep sense of the
word within the the dialog and man as
the sacred ever that well at least
sacredness is that ever-present in the
Platonic dialogues as well it constantly
in its invoke like in you know Socrates
even ends the Phaedrus by with a prayer
for to the god Pan and and whatever
other gods were present throughout the
dialogue right so I think talking about
while trying to also simultaneously
invoke and that's what you always have
to do in participant observation right
about the the sacredness I think is also
relevant because once we start getting
into this this idea of love and interesa
if maybe if I use the Latin that'll be
better we try to get into the so let's
let's say that let's let's you say the
love aspect is the an agogic mutually
accelerating disclosure and then the
interests 'singing to the depths right
the sinking to the ontological depths so
we've got the love and we've got the in
right the interests a they're going on I
think that is going to take us because
it's taking us into it's taking us into
the womb from which you know meaning as
connection is born it's taking us into
sacredness it's taking us into the
experience that when when we get this
kind of deep coupling that the Hebrew
word to off comes to mind here when we
get this kind of deep coupling with the
love and the interesa right we're we're
getting into realizing again playing
light as you know that i use that word
to mean both a subjective and an
objective and thereby convey the
transgender we're realizing in a
completely interdependent interdependent
fashion the open endedness of our
relevance realization machinery and the
inexhaustible Ness of the of the
combinatorial explosive nature of
reality and that when those if we have
just the combinatorial explosive nature
that's horror that's terror if we
just the open-endedness and it's not
disclosing anything that's that's a cut
that's a kind of hunger right that's
kind of hunger right but when when the
two are coupled together such that they
are mutually revealing usually
disclosing the open endedness of the
relevance realization and the
inexhaustible Ness so that I'm
experiencing the depths of reality and
the depths of my relevance realization
as a continually flowing fount of
continually emerging emerging
intelligibility that I think is I think
I could make a very good case that in
many mystical traditions and
philosophical traditions that's their
understanding of sacredness as an
experience I used the word sacredness to
talk about the experience and then I use
the word the sacred or sacred typically
the sacred to try to refer to whatever
proposal we have as to what the
metaphysical or ontological basis of
that experience is but I think this the
experience of sacredness is very much
and that's why it's always filled with
awe and reverence and even a tinge of
horror because it's getting us it's
opening us up to that sort of
fundamental the no thingness of at the
at the I don't I want to get at the base
of relevance realization and the no
thinness at the base of of the way the
reality discloses itself to us and so I
think that's a new way of trying to
recapture so I'm trying to be very
careful here which I'm trying to bring
some new language to something that I
think nevertheless has an ancient
heritage and legacy I think a lot of the
mystical traditions and the wisdom
traditions speak about sacredness this
way because it's it's a kind as a sense
of sacredness that is deeply connected
to the cultivation of self transcendence
and wisdom and I offer this as an
alternative to another prevalent and a
long-standing notion of sacredness as
perfection where perfectionist
understood as coming to rest coming to
completion and that was what I always
I've always objected to the word Telos
because perfection and completion are
bound well etymologically to the word
Telos and so that that
that sense of a TV ology is it that's
the aspect of that I was resisting and
challenging because I think the notion
of that what I'm experiment and here's
where I'm not only criticizing sort of
standard classical theism there's a way
which I'm criticizing Plato here because
there's definitely places where he gets
into talking about this in terms of
perfection and I think there's there's a
mistake here it's unclear what he means
by that but it's fair that people have
come away from that and saying oh the
sacred is something that is perfect that
generates the experience of perfection
Descartes certainly does this in the
meditations right and that's what this
is all about and I think I think that's
just a profound mistake I think that's
just a profound mistake so I think that
one of the things that dialogo reveals
and here think about the logos now as as
the an agog a as the love and also the
interests say the deepening right and
it's taking on a life of its own and
then birthing us and giving us life from
itself right I think the sacredness in
diello those needs to be the sacredness
not of perfection but the sacredness of
the inexhaustible hmm yeah I hear that
John that's beautiful I agree I agree
you know I
mmm so so what is so there's so we are
not we are not we are not perfecting the
sacred but we are continually optimizing
our capacity to make sacred yeah yeah so
that's that's where the analogy to
evolution biological evolution is so
helpful to me if you I mean and people
do fall prey to the temptation to think
that evolution is a ladder that there's
a TV ology and thermal biological
evolution of a cultural evolution that's
I'd I understand that that's different I
just want to use the standard model of
biological evolution to explain my
analogy right right there isn't a ladder
evolution isn't
isn't seeking the perfect final complete
design what it's always doing is this
has worked for a moment or two in
geological time which means it's a
reliable basis for me to make something
new now from that which will then if it
works will be a reliable basis for me to
make something new which if it lands to
use Peter Lindbergh favorite phrase the
phrase I hear encircling if it lands
then it gives me a a stable platform
from which I can make something new
again and so on and so forth I'm not
trying to bring it to completion and
here's where here's where I want to say
another point because this this relates
again to dialog and the difference
between dialogue and story even though
we put dialogue in story but so I think
narrative is psychologically
indispensable for us developmentally I
think if we don't cultivate narrative we
can't narrative teaches me to grasp
non-logical identity it teaches me what
it means to say I'm identical to that
four year old and I'll be identical to
the 75 year old man who is retired
so narrative gives me deep practice in a
temporarily extend itself that has non
logical identity and that is so
important for my rationality and my
cognition of my metacognition
I think narrative is indispensable but I
don't think narrative is final or
complete a lot of the traditions and so
there's some psychological work say that
people can move to sort of a post
narrative state in which they operate I
think you can see various friends of
Buddhism Taoism and stoicism advocating
moving to a trans narrative state now
why do I say that because the thing
about narrative right is right if you
try to impose a narrative on biological
evolution what people do then they get
it fundamentally wrong because narrative
is teleologically oriented it moves
towards closure it moves towards
finality it moves towards perfection and
they live happily ever after
narrative right ultimately while
psychologically indispensable to giving
us all of the machinery we need to
exempt for wisdom ultimately I think has
to be left behind if we're going to
operate within dialogue the way it does
that's why although you there's clearly
sort of some narrative elements the
sonic dialogue many of them don't end
with narrative closure they're not
they're not they're not resolved
completed stories and the relationship
between the dialogues is not one of
narrative it's one of sort of an ecology
in which they're talking to each other
and check it's a dialogic relationship
there's there's a meta dialogue between
each of the individual dialogues and I
think that we have to be paying more
more and more attention to that and I
think there's been a deep connection for
deep historical reasons between the
ontology of perfection and the
symbolization of narrative we've tended
to think of narrative sacredness and
perfection as as as inextricably bound
together again I want to be really
careful about this I'm not denying right
I'm not denying the importance of
narrative I'm not denying the fact that
often what people are trying to express
with perfections they feel as something
is perpetually transcendent to them I'm
just saying there are post narrative
post reflection ways I think of
referring to what people are standing
towards in a way that doesn't
misrepresent the kind of as I said it
before
the kind of formulation we need the kind
of yep the kind of as you said the way
we're presencing in order for deilogos
to work mm-hmm yes yes and and we've and
then we find ourselves here and now in a
collaborative always collaborative
participatory making realization of the
course that we can be on together in
coherence that enables us to continue to
be on course together is still this
notion of course the Darth you speak
about and yeah and so they're not sir
let's let's bring this in here because
what because because yes track that's
why that's why we use the word discourse
that's what we use the word discourse
we're where we're picking up on the fact
that there is a kid there is a coursing
there is a coursing going on and and of
course das was also bound up with the
sense that there's a course to history
right and of course we use course of
course we use course as a way of
pointing to a a pedagogical paths all of
these things yes very much okay now I'd
now I'm going to see if I can bring in a
frame here that that may well be
concordant it may be meaningfully
different but it is if I want to bring
it forth then I'd be leaving something
important to the side because I'd like
please I'd like to take what we've
present here and then see if if again we
can cut because I'm still I'm interested
in let's say for the sake of this
conversation seems part of what seems to
be driving me I'm interested in in in
saving keeping what is necessary and
helpful in the notion of Tilos while
while already already in some sense
absolutely changing it by by saying okay
we are only going to take forward for
the purpose of this conversation that a
self making I continually self making T
loss and it's not a finality of
thickness that we're looking for okay
Evan Thompson Thompson talks about this
and living things as an imminent TD
teleology beautiful right and he's
harkening back to cos there and so and
that living things because they're self
oriented it's they have an imminent TV
ology and that the TV ology is
completely recursive the t the the the
purpose is to maintain the ability to
like it's you say it's it's it's the
purpose of maintaining the self making
yes yes beautiful so we are absolutely
on the same page with that what very
much I have no objection to that sense
of teleology I have no objects on
whatsoever
I think it's integral if we're going to
understand Otto poiesis and aspiration I
I think it's integral beautiful okay
okay excellent
what we encounter in experience and what
we also containing within our lives is
the
Supreme depths of our lineage and the
vast unknown of the future and also the
inconsistency of duration as we
experience it different experiences we
can you will commonly hear people refer
to you know like it felt like three
years but in that few short weeks or
whatever it felt like hours and it was
just me a seconds or minutes and we can
talk about this thing perhaps from the
perspective of the brain and the release
of chemicals and stuff like that that's
that's fine but but there's actually but
I I am I am very influenced by Berg so
on as I know you are as well I heard you
in a conversation I heard you really
appreciating that notion of jus ray and
for me there with JP yeah yeah with yeah
which reappear and given my interest and
exploration with psychedelics as well as
other kinds of practices I am I am well
aware of the the a temporality and the
vast expansiveness that can seemingly be
experienced right and become very very
difficult to integrate into a coherent
theory but perhaps and the right
dialogue in fact we can begin to work
with these things because ok so here
here here here we are this self making
to enable further self making must
realize itself according to patterns it
must like it must be it's it's humble
before and within the patterns that
already enable it and yes and it deeply
participates in the realization of
patterns that will continue to afford
its flourishing if we were to step back
and look at that we're not seeing chaos
we are with the right tools in mind
seeing a certain pattern and the certain
kind of pattern that can be beautifully
artistically represented people might
use a mandala they might use just a
beautiful image of you know a human
being I'm I'm I'm struck I'm struck by
feminine beauty and I'm struck by how
there's a sense of a timeless alluring
draw
whirring forth the beauty in it and a
magnificence and and there's a sense in
which there's a sense in which there's a
sense in which if I attend to myself I
am I can become a more caring a better
person in whatever way we want to wrap
that up over that over a period of time
I want to be I want to be able to be
more and more appropriately realize my
potential and I and I feel very strongly
that in so doing I can more effectively
contribute and be incurring an occurring
relationship with the world and I want
to look at that aesthetic and go this
here to me is meaningful and there was a
course here that would there was a there
is a way that was walked which had a
pattern to it which while itself is not
in any deep sense the only one it's not
fixed that's not what there is there is
there is there is was a cycle of
development there you know I loved and I
let go
appropriately and I open myself again
and I faced courageously the depths of
experience and so ok so the final thing
to add into this Ike and then I'm would
absolutely love to hear your responses
is this is this you don't you don't put
the modes of orientation which enable
that continued pattern making the humble
for the past that you know learning as
much as possible and then opening up and
creating that future because we must
create our future we must create it in
an important sense by not making many of
the mistakes we've made heretofore I
follow the line of thinking of a Jordan
Hall an awful lot with respect to
civilization design and what have you
but it's so ok so that's how I stopped
there and then there there's another
piece they introduced but let's see if
how that sort of sits ya know that so
there's lots of points of residence that
are coming up for me so there's there's
a you were talking about sort of the
deep connection between temporality and
how ontology can put a call upon us so
and you see this you see this in higher
states of consciousness when people
experience the really real they
experience what I call on to normativity
they feel because
because meaning is about being connected
they want to be deeply connected so they
want an increasingly more intimate
conformity with this really real and so
they will transform their lives and
their identity so it deeply empowers the
aspiration to transformation then you're
talking about I so and that again I
think that's very much a platonic model
and then you were looking something that
of course Plato sees is bound up with
that well how this is we are bringing
Plato and Berks on together that's the
district bees are very interesting and
odd thing to touch to pose them that way
but Plato of course talks a great deal
about beauty and that it has a capacity
to to inspire us to aspirations Ascari
talks about this in her book about how
beauty prepares us for truth and justice
because of the way it transforms our
sensibility and transforms our
motivation so that we become more and
more capable of seeing the truth we
become more more capable of acting
justly and so well there while beauty
isn't truth it is a deep affordance of a
aspirational path to becoming more
truthful and to becoming more just and I
think all of that I mean and I think
Iris Murdoch saw that that was clearly
what was in the center of a lot of the
Platonic and the neo platonic tradition
so I think all of that is very
interesting it resonates with everything
you just said and then let's bring it
back to the thing that started it which
was the the difference experiences of
temporality because we're talking again
about what we're talking about this Anna
Garden process we're talking about the
process that the way Beauty couples me
in such a way that my identity is
restructured my my sensibility my
salience landscape is restructured so
the way the world can disclose itself
because beauty and love are bound
intricately up together you get that
usually accelerating disclosure and
beauty is often a call to that it's
often right if it's right it has that
kind of call upon us it draws us forth
but then there is this and then you know
and of course this is a high to gary
notion to I suppose but there's there's
the sense in which we're moving and and
this is something I've talked to
with JP JP Lamar so I've had a bunch of
really excellent conversations with him
I'm gonna have one very shortly with him
and with Mary Cohen so I'm looking
forward to that a lot but there's a
sense in which I think about white head
because in white head white weighted of
course is deeply a platonic he clearly
indicates that but he's also very deeply
consonant with a lot of Brooks song so
maybe he's somebody we could use to to
talk about this bridge between them but
what I see what I see in Whitehead as I
see this bipolar ontology let me try and
articulate this a little you definitely
you know he says that you know there
many are gathered into the one that
becomes something new so everything
everything is interpenetrating
everything else and and then it causes
new emergence so you've got this if
you'll allow me these metaphors if you
have this bottom-up emergence but he
talks about the fact that you you put
your finger on this the way right the
way things emerge they emerge in a way
that again we get the sense that
possibility and you know that I take
possibility to be a real category of not
just a conjectural category that
possibility and this is this is
whiteheads notion that the Platonic
forms were in some sense a way in which
possibility is structured and if you'll
allow me a neo platonic notion that that
structuring of possibility emanates into
the patterns that are forded to emerge
within the emergence and then those
patterns of course access the structured
possibility there's a way in which the
bottom-up emergence and the top-down
emanation are completely inter
penetrating with each other is why I've
been so deeply attracted to the work of
John Scott a Sarah Gina from within the
Christian tradition he's this Titanic
figure and it like in from the 9th
century and that he but he's also
regarded as a heretic but it's
interesting because he's seen as the
great synthesizer of Eastern and Western
Christian Christendom Christianity and
Neoplatonism he was he was elevated to
very high status in the court and then
he was asked to produce the doctrine in
and he did the paraphilia on the
division of nature and then when this
came out
Suri's world around him because he tried
to articulate this idea of creation
right as something that should be
understood as being the complete
interpenetration of e emanation from
eternity and emergence within time and
that instead of thinking them as
opposite we have to think of them
so here's metaphysics he doesn't just
use a dialectic as he writes the his
pair for Seon as as a dialogue but
dialectic is the ontological structure
he feel he sees like in reality itself
that it's inherently dialectic precisely
because of the complete top-to-bottom
interpenetration of emanation and
emergence within creation and and so and
then and then - and then to top it all
off because of the particular notion of
God which i think is where the heresy
comes in
he sees all of that as one with God's
inherent self creativity that when God
is creating that that is always just an
act of self creation so it's that this
dialectic of the dialectic of creation
is is is inseparable from God's ongoing
self creativity and so he see again
again it's a different notion of the
sacred as this ongoing inexhaustible
production of intelligibility as opposed
to the at rest perfection that's why I
imagine he was regarded as heretical
he's now sort of come back around and
people are starting to consider him much
more carefully even within theological
circles precisely because this this
ontology that he talks about seems to be
so apt for talking about these these two
things that we're trying to bring
together within our worldview and I
would add apt for providing a deep
grounding a deep ontological grounding
for discursive dialectic like what you
and I are doing right here right now
yeah it's beautiful it's beautiful
okay so two things come to mind both
take a long time to say let me see if I
can reduce both quickly so that
hopefully we don't lose either the first
is that I would continue to like to hone
in on what I mean by modes of
orientation yes I would and the second
is just how much I'm interested in the
continued discussion and careful
experimentation with with the embedding
and invitation of more people to
participate in community regarding what
we're speaking about in such a fashion
that well that that well does it justice
cares for it but I'm also interested in
the I do feel a sense of urgency and I
appreciate the importance of being slow
and smooth I deeply do and I also feel a
sense of urgency and I and I feel that
in our culture we are lacking the pillar
where a polis can be together and
mutually inform each other and disclose
themselves in this fashion so that we
can become more in touch with the state
of our collective moment and our
connection to ecology and how we can
actually begin to take powerful
decisions powerful decisions must mean
they should be taken from from an
already exhibited capacity to presence
oneself in relationship with this very
process of the generation and
development of wisdom if they're not
coming from that then it's it's it's
deeply it's is actually horrifying it's
horrifying yes and which is why we're
okay so that's that and but it maybe we
could go the modes of orientation route
first which is easy first of all I like
that
I think it's excellent and I'd like so
okay I want to turn back things to you
very momentarily I've noticed that at
crucial points you invoke this as
something that was paying a pivotal
meaning capacity to turn things playing
a pivotal role in one note one moment if
the OREA by the way it's important to
step back and in a high to garyun
fashion like I just didn't like you've
done to step back and to degree to which
you can and sometimes we make mistakes
about this and I've made some myself but
did agree to which we can and so more
education is needed but did you read to
we can pay attention to the etymology
try to give life back to the words so
that they can resonate in a way that is
beyond our normal everyday manipulation
and control of them give them back some
of their being so they're not just words
that we have so like I said so we've got
and we're trying to do this right now I
think with modes of orientation and I
was trying to do it when I I was
invoking this term pivotal that you
invoke modes of orientation because it's
a pivot it allows us to move and shift
things that are otherwise heavy or hard
to move because we've we've we found a
balance and a point at which such
redirection becomes possible for us so
you know the ways in which mode of
orientation is pivotal I think is what
what I was picking up on and what I want
to try and explore with you I just
wanted to make that note again that
theory a note about the value of rien
pregnat in our words as much as possible
by paying attention to their meta
ferocity and to their etymology yeah
that's that's beautiful and it's
something that you evidence to an
incredible degree in your lectures and I
think it's one of the one of the many
chief reasons why they afford people to
open up their conceptions so much and
yeah it's great
so so okay so modes of orientation then
fundamentally I don't know fundament a
key piece in the role that these modes
of orientation are playing is in our
relationship
to death and dissolution and broadly
speaking the chaos that can enter our
experience the horror as well right that
there dislodging there how is it how can
we find ourselves again how can we find
connection again from a place of
disconnection in some respects that's
one that's one thing that's important
and the other is also how we can front
up to change how we can from a place of
sort of coherence that's become
stagnated and stultified decide bravely
to move over the boundary right to
confront and attend and it seems to me
that the capacity to attend in different
modes is is sort of um it's it's it's
hard for me to imagine the pictures with
that we're speaking about without those
fundamental building blocks of just how
also poetic processes can be in
relationship which is other than their
immediate domain of auto police's at all
how can we how can we transgress and
trance frame our boundaries without in
some sense the the courage to be with
the not knowing and ultimately to to
surrender in some sense and also to
confront the two terms that were pivotal
for me in making sense of some deep
psychedelic experience I had were
confrontation and surrender I'm not
attached to either there is a negative
and positive mode of each but they're
just what the terms are maybe I would be
interested to hear how you would take
the this kind of discussion and I'm not
attached to having to do it through the
lens I'm bringing sure so there's a lot
there's a lot there I like so let's
let's let's gather together logos gather
together so the things belong together
that that you know there's this there's
this there's this encouragement and in
caring that is bound up with the mode of
orientation as you said because
as what we're facing is we're facing the
real possibility of dissolution a kind
of death and so it's interesting there's
a term of course in dynamical systems
that tries to point to this which is
criticality our system is critical when
it is undergoing enough dissolution that
it can restructure and reframe itself
but if it takes too much then it will
actually fall into this dissolution so
that's why it's called critical it's
it's playing on both senses of the word
critical I think in a very nice fashion
so I think one of the things that's
critical one of the things that can get
us into criticality and that we don't
our culture is not good at and this is
why I've spent some time on I keep
coming back to it is serious play and
serious play I think is I think I think
it's it's it's it's something that has
been exacted you see in in mammals not
just in us right serious play is I think
indispensable for qualitative
development the kind of development
you're talking about here the
development that the kind there's
development that is quantitative where
you just acquire more and more knowledge
and more information and then there's
qualitative development which I think
you can best understand as development
that must pass through criticality to
get to the developmental stage you can't
just keep sort of more of the same and
acquire more you actually have that you
need new functionality and so you have
to put the current functionality at risk
it has to go into a period of
criticality and what we see is and and
you know and I think this just is
convergent with the brilliant work of La
Paul and the brilliant work of Agnes
Keller - but we can't sort of and and
and voter's work about you can't infer a
stronger logic from a weaker logic you
can't infer yourself through these
transformations you have to you have to
aspire through them and I tried to argue
that this is that the notion of serious
play was part of what was at work in in
nos in the Gnostics or at least that in
within nauseous because gnosis is again
the Greek word for that deep kind of
participatory
knowing and and of course the gnostics
they sought to place themselves into
exactly the kind of existential risk
that you're talking about here the conic
talks about that how transgressive of
their so the point about the the serious
play is it's it's how I hate human
beings it's it's it's how we put
ourselves into a a a what's called
metastability a state of criticality so
that qualitative development is actually
possible for us while also setting up a
whole bunch of constraints and systems
so that we get back out or reverse out
if needed we don't over and completely
commit so that like we there we create a
situation within serious play in which
we can taste and touch the criticality
but error is not completely disastrous
for us there's there's more error
tolerance so the child is playing with
the plastic sword right and you know and
perhaps you know and I'm not saying we
should have in a military militaristic
culture I'm just using it for ease of
export of explanation you know in the
point about the plan ID Tai Chi with the
wooden sword there we go
I did shoot country with a wooden sword
it's serious play because you know I'm
putting myself into
you know clumsiness following I can hurt
myself for sure but because it's a
wooden sword then there's it's done
within a particular context as opposed
to combat with a military sort error
isn't quite as disastrous there's much
more error tolerance so that I can and I
want to use this we're very very
deliberately I can play with the
possibilities to try and get that dot
that sense of okay how do i how do i
course my way through this how do i
course my way through this and i think
why it's a problem for us in our
culture's we don't have we we don't we
don't think about or talk about or do a
lot to valorize or validate serious play
play is either trivialized into
fun for us or we think if it's important
in serious it must be work and then with
there's a step and an algorithm and a
recipe for getting there which of course
is not how development works and the
place where cultures generally do
serious play for adults and also perhaps
for children but primarily for adults is
ritual that's what ritual is it's the
place where we do serious play I mean if
you go into church and it's in and you
open yourself up mode of orientation to
the serious play that's going on there
if that's viable for you I'm not saying
is what I don't think would be viable
for me but if it's viable for you right
and you get involved with the serious
play of the Eucharist or let's say it's
Easter the portrayal of the crucifixion
and the resume like whoo like you're
playing with your identity and you're
playing with some of your deepest
effective machinery and you're really
allowing you but you're you you're
involved with a kind of profound serious
play that nevertheless there's a
community around you there's a tradition
around you you've been taken into a
space outside of the ongoing profane
space of the world so you you're safe
from the world for a while so there's a
lot more error tolerance there's a lot
more support and there's a ritual that
other people have tried so you're not
just starting it in an other didactic
fashion from scratch and so I think
there are there are deep connections
between the meaning crisis and our
inability to take up the appropriate
modes of modes of orientation precisely
because our culture is really really
poor are dealing with serious play like
and notice how how poorly and I mean
that even economically we reward people
who who live lives in which serious play
like musicians and artists and other
people who have decided that serious
play is something that needs to be
exemplified and enacted we tend to say
but that's not as important as work you
know this Protestant work at work we're
a card maker or you know all that's not
that we shouldn't work I'm not saying
that but we I mean again another symptom
in crisis and this has become a
pervasive we have a culture and work
workaholism right we're call ism what is
it workaholism is i think it's not
accepted workaholics yeah it's it's
basically people people do not know how
to be other than work so they do not
know how to become really because they
can't engage in serious play and han
talks about this in the agony of ecstasy
they get into a you know a mode of self
exploitation where they're constantly
driven to achieve to achieve to achieve
and they can't engage in actual
development in serious play so when
they're not working all they can do is
to drop into a kind of two / almost a
lethargy of
luxury they like so the idea that that
something really important goes on all
you're doing is basically recovering so
that you can go back to work and so i
think that's also a very important
social problem that is feeding back into
the meeting crisis because of the way it
is foreclosing for us access to the
modes of orientation that are most
appropriate for deep development yeah
that's beautiful and it's remarkable to
me because you tied the link there
between modes of orientation and the
development of a space within culture
where people can precisely come together
and seriously play in the fashion do any
describe doing it we're doing it right
now and this is what I mean about and
and this is why I often so I vertically
don't respond to comments in the videos
because first of all there's too many
and I couldn't I can't and secondly
people are people are often just
extemporaneous you know expressing and
that's fine I don't that's fine do that
and they often they want to talk to
other people all of that and there's all
those reasons sometimes if somebody
catches me on a factual error then I'll
admit it on that way or if there's a
there's somebody else that I'm like you
if you commented I'd respond because we
have an ongoing dialogue and I know that
I have access to you
a deep dialogue not the superficial
format of commenting on YouTube which I
think could be very irresponsible in in
so many ways
so but right I've replied a couple times
when people have commented in my
dialogues with Jordan Hall and they say
like this isn't going anywhere and I'm
trying to it's like no no stop thinking
of this as work right what Jordan is
doing is he is exemplifying a very
profound kind of serious play he's
showing us how to participatory knowing
what's serious what serious play in
dialogue is like because he is trying to
afford development much more than he's
trying to come to a conclusive
proposition and that's what needs to be
paid very careful attention to yeah
beautiful I absolutely agree and that's
certainly a deep reason why I respect
Jordan so much for he's doing and I feel
that I feel a deep resonance actually on
that point you know generally speaking
moving around in the world I'm engaging
with people much the same as this I
think usually I with more with a bit
more lightness not that I haven't felt
light in this but there's also the sense
in which that this is recorded and I'm
sort of sitting still I actually like to
move around quite a lot you know I'm
yeah and but but but fundamentally the
way in to meaningful relationships with
people is almost always maybe it is
always I just want to have a bit of
humility and speaking extemporaneously
like this is to meet someone precisely
where they're at with present seeing the
part of themselves in relationship to
you that is ready and able and willing
to transform itself in a developmental
fashion even in a small way like want to
show up as Who I am with what I have and
the way into all of these things is so I
mean it's it's its myriad its infinite
because it's precisely where that
particular unique instantiation of a
person is in their
life yet fundamentally we're all going
through the same cycles it's still the
theory theory a dance it's still
checking in and being there and making
sense of where we can together
cultivating a shared space of care and
sense relying on much of what our
culture has given us yet at the same
time drawing in some create co-creating
some potential together that is joyous
in its opening up of the world in that
way for us then and there John I'm
conscious now that we're coming to I
don't know how long we have left so I
can go a little bit after six to make up
for my time a little bit past this
schedule two hours to make up for that
gap that we've countered so that you can
have a more complete thing but let's say
about another sort of 25 minutes I was
okay beautiful okay excellent okay then
so let's let's see how let's see it's
you know it's it's an incredible I feel
so grateful to have this kind of
opportunity and I have worked fairly
hard to have this kind of opportunity
but there's a thing in dialog that I
feel I'm bringing people together to do
this kind of thing and contend with deep
issues and I would love there's so many
beautiful areas of dialogue and places
we could go but it's almost feels like
I've got a special power right now
because I can drop in I can drop into
myself and drop a question and I can
throw it over to you and you've sort of
agree so it's a hilarious you know it's
like the world can open up to me just
from doing that and it's it's quite
remarkable so so I'm going to if you
don't mind take that opportunity to do
just that
and see in what way we can we can
unleash what you can have to offer
hmm
hmm oh this is it
so hmm okay so there's a few areas of
inquiry that have come to mind first of
all I was really motivated by this
notion of joy and in what sense in what
sense we you can create for us hear us
or speak to how of how of how where may
be ripe
you know creation of a an element or
space within culture that can afford a
sort of joyful opening of people's
expression and then you know what came
to me John I felt that maybe they are
you know metaphorically they're the sort
of opponent processing of that and I
felt I felt into a a difficulty and a
certain trauma of our time and and that
is going to be a bit of a lateral jump
but it may be somewhat resonant and that
for me is one experienced I think by
both men and women by both but in a both
masculine sense and a feminine sense but
there is a the the whole world of me too
and just not what me too is specifically
but what it's tapping into in sort of a
certain disconnection and in some sense
and inappropriate kind of relationship
at an environment fundamentally of not
caring there's a there's a deep sense in
which an interlocking sense of care has
not been managed for whatever reason for
the psyches of people involved in this
millio that we find ourselves in and
something I've experienced is that there
is a there's a particular I don't know
and what maybe not a particular but
there's a deep sense of a a woundedness
for both masculine and feminine but
let's maybe if concentrated on the
feminine perhaps they have to be taken
together that's true surely
poor sense and I think people don't do
that enough really speak to both
masculinity and femininity together but
there's a there's a block there's
somehow an environment of safety that
must be cultivated so presence a certain
kind of I would like to say and it has
to be metaphorical is a distinctly
feminine kind of energy a feminine kind
of vulnerability in certain spaces for
that to be present but not in not to be
looked for that not to be an exposure
for that presence seeing not to be seen
then as prey you know what I mean that's
like it's there has and it's enabling of
that vulnerability because without that
and the appropriate relationship there
in men and women seriously playing
together you know joy is going to be
hampered joy is going to be concerned
with whether or not it's vulnerable
expression is in some sense unsafe so
what are your thoughts on that mode of
inquiry oh that's that's very that's
very very important one of the things I
try to do is in order to discharge some
of the reactivity around the words I
often shift to yin and yang rather than
feminine and masculine because that
those tend to have a more ontological
Association as as opposed to they're now
highly politicized understanding of
masculine and feminine not that there
aren't important political issues there
are not I'm not denying the history of
feminism or its value I'm just saying
that sometimes it's hard to talk about
the things you want to talk about I
notice how there's trepidation yeah how
you're moving around these words so the
yin and yang aspects to me call me in so
wonderfully when I move from adversarial
Procera framing to an opponent
processing and then I see this very much
at work in circling in which I men and
women in in the circling right and you
the there is all kinds of overly
simplistic things Oh everybody's the
same
that's ridiculous being a man being a
woman that makes a difference pretend it
doesn't is his pretense ah but also to
come up with simple you know
categorizations of what that means is
also that's why again I try to use this
you know yang because these these are
much more comprehensive and Eve and you
know multi vocal terms right and and and
there and and and there they in the Dow
in the symbol of the Dow they are
represented in dynamic relationship and
interpenetrating each other with no with
no sexual intent meant there and and so
I see I see that the people that come
into circling and I'm deeply grateful to
to meet these people and I can even see
it within a person like when when guy is
doing his thing or retort and is doing
his thing and I mean that thing with
respect I don't mean if I like I see
there's a deep reverence for the
expansion of the yang and the traction
of the end the the variety the the
attempt to project of the yang the
attempt to sensitize at the end and that
and if they're there if they're flowing
and you get this scent of they're
they're both sort of parametric
constraints on the self-organizing
process it goes on and people aren't
trying to pin them down or position
themselves as representing one of this
constraints rather what they want to do
is they want to participate as fully as
possible if the rhythm of the process
that's taking place within the space
that is constituted by the by the
constraints so they're trying to hold
the constraints within opponent
processing rather than position
themselves adversarial as representative
of the polls and put them into some kind
of competition with each other now I
think all of that is very very important
now we have to take great care because
that that that is a very real
possibility and it is a possibility that
both the men and the women I think in
the circling deeply value I
that's that is my I have come I have a
strong conviction that that's what I'm
seeing in the circle so are you still
there Tim yes I'm here I think they're
first yes yeah you fro yeah okay did you
hear everything I said about both yes
both the men and women are deeply value
okay
and so I I want to acknowledge all of
that and I want to acknowledge it
reverentially and I want to recommend it
as something you should be paying more
attention to that instead of positioning
and adversarial we can we can hold the
opponent processing and move to the
space given by the constraints right I
want to acknowledge that reverentially
while also acknowledging that we have to
address all the traumatic damage that's
been done and by the kind of disconnect
you're talking about the way in which we
for all kinds of cultural historical and
psychopathological regions have hurt
each other around you know issues of
gender and masculine and the feminine
III I think I think I think what I want
to say there is my one criticism about
how many people talk about for lack of a
better adjective and it's not quite the
right adjective but it's the one that
I'm gonna use right now how people talk
about the political aspect if that's the
one criticism I have is it seems to me
that the expression of anger and
resentment on both sides or multiple
sites I guess is being prioritized over
trying to create a shared goal of
bringing about healing from the trauma
and here's how the two points connect
together I think if we recover the
yin-yang dynamism that can tell us that
it that healing is really possible and
that therefore we should be balancing
the needed criticism with the ultimate
prioritizing of the goal of healing and
that is not to trivialize or equate
everybody's suffering or to do anything
simplistic like that
right I'm not I'm I hope I'm not being
stupid here in that fashion but I do
think that you're running out of time
and we've got to figure out how to more
deeply live together and love together
and work and play together and develop
together if we're gonna save things and
so we've got to give more priority to
the healing we just have to do I mean I
don't see a real alternative for all of
us together yes yes yes and the movement
we not us in terms of us and them this
how can we as part of this yeah this
opponent processing is I could the
rhythm I I love the metaphors I speak so
much most mostly to open up to people
about where I'm where I'm thinking and
feeling and how I'm being in the world
is through the metaphor of rhythm and
music what I'm finding most powerful is
this notion of the deep drums stuff tap
in and feel into the deep drums that are
present you know all the noise all the
noise it is a it's an innate capacity of
all of us to dig deep yeah yeah and I
like the shamanic associations that it's
calling for I think that's I think
that's very wonderful that's wonderful
thank you that's very I like that
metaphor a lot too deep drums yeah so I
think I think you know I it worries me
because we're you know the adversarial
processing is becoming so so prominent
and such it's being sort of indicated as
so meshed with the only way to have
power and influence I do worry
about our ability to get back to the
sense of opponent processing see the to
me one of the one of the crucial
differences is in opponent processing
and this is again the difference between
dialogue and monologue it's the
difference between phyleus ophea and phi
lea nykeya the love of wisdom versus the
love of victory right is that we what we
should share above both of us always is
a commitment to the process as opposed
to the victory of whatever position
we're advocating and see democracies
were supposed to and they did for a long
time work and people being committed to
the process and the idea that the
conflict within right between the
parties was ultimately the best way to
embody self-correction that what we were
actually invested in was because I think
the ultimate value of democracy is its
capacity for self correction that's what
sets it above the other systems and I
think once it loses self correction it
becomes what Winston Churchill I mean
it's the worst - next in which the
Churchill said it's the worst system
next to all the rest but I think if you
remove that the commitment is self
correction then it just simply becomes
the worst system right and and so I
think that you have to have a commitment
to the process because of an unwavering
understanding and appreciation and
reverence for how much self correction
is continually needed by all and
therefore why the opponent processing
must be respected above and beyond your
own particular party and position at all
times and when democracies have that I
think they function very very well and
when we lose that which I think we're
losing all around and especially in sort
of the major democracies like the United
States and and Britain I mean we seem to
have lost this capacity for
understanding the need by all for self
correction and therefore the commitment
to the superlative valuing of the
process and the self correction
in over our particular goals and our
particular party in a particular
position if we the we to which the
democracies have have lost that
commitment these agree to which we've
entered into very serious trouble and I
think you know the fact that it's
becoming difficult to take a stand above
one's party for one's country how
difficult that's becoming United
States's how is I grew up with the
Americans being the epitome of
patriotism that Americanism was almost
like a secular religion and now
Americanism is dead and people oh no no
no if you are not committed to the
process into the country over your
position in your party Americanism is
dead
it is dead dad dad Oh John it's it's
very very powerful there's um there's
there's there's something we can
presence here that brings this to life
in a way that's even in some sense more
horrifying which is which is that you
know I follow English politics quite a
lot particularly in this brexit period
watching Parliament and what-have-you
and what what seems to be one of the key
markers of a successful politician in
this combative sense not in this deep
sense my god not in this deep sense is
the capacity to perform as if you were
extending the hand but you're not
extending the hand you're deeply you're
you're deeply insinuating that the other
side is is not to be leveraged yeah and
the level or the level of articulation
capacity the Boris Johnson and speak and
what's his name extremely posh in his
presentation and Wow Jacob Riis MOG and
his capacity to deliver to deliver
communication in such a in such a
flowing way he he evokes the sense of
the gentleman in just an incredible
incredible degree and it has me buying
into it when he speaks an awful lot and
then there's part of me that it's like
if that if that is really functioning by
way of if it's if you know it has just
you know through the little sly lines of
the Communists on the other side or just
the a certain kind of division to to the
the energy like it's it's not it's not
extending the hand to what is what what
is virtuous like what where where the
virtue is coming from it you know
sometimes when we are outraged it may be
the case that much of what we're saying
turns to noise quite quickly but the
very motivation to be presenting
something we care about in that
performative way we all be being
vulnerable with that that has to be
spoken to and heard right it has to be
heard and appreciated and there's a
sense in which just how good at just how
good at acting as though we are building
bridges but fundamentally not building
bridges is is it is a core dangerous the
performance of authenticity in that in
that deep sense rather than rather than
a true offering becomes yes yes yes the
praetor's yeah I've tried to I've tried
to think about that very deeply in a way
that would call me to my own personal
response what are the markers that I'm
actually entering into dialogue as
opposed to earth science or protects
I've tried to look for the degree to
which I'm open to an insight from the
other I'm open to acknowledging a good
critic
the other I'm open to dialog in with
people who and I do do this who have
ontological religious commitments other
than mine and trying to it's let me give
you a clear example jonathan pazzo who I
deeply respect um you know they're much
critted a committed Christian Eastern
Orthodoxy he made a criticism you know
John's talking but you know the the all
disease ecology to practice but what he
tell him to talk about is very
individualistic and he's leaving he's
leaving out you know what was in the
ecclesia the gathering together the
collective and I thought that's that's
that's right I took that criticism and
let's remember what this used to mean I
took that criticism to heart that's one
of the things that motivated me to take
a look at circling to get involved in
these collective psycho technologies
precisely because uh you know I took
Jonathan's criticism seriously it was
like that no that's a very very good
point
I take Paul's criticism about when I'm
talking about the religion that's not a
religion about the issues of scalability
and you know what do you do that's gonna
do you know what how is it gonna match
up to something like what tradition gave
us yeah I take I so they're you know we
have to remember and this goes along
with serious play it between accepting
and rejecting there is the important
liminal transformative place of taking
seriously taking seriously it doesn't
mean oh I agree you're right or no
you're wrong let's fight about it it's
like I'm gonna take it seriously and I'm
gonna try and see what insight is in
there you know open myself up try as
much as I can to self correction it
doesn't mean that I'm gonna sort of just
give ground because then that's also not
of service to the person that I've been
dialog with right but the this idea and
this is why I doing all this work with
Neil Ferraro on plausibility as opposed
to certainty because certainty is about
right about coming to conclusions which
are very rare to actually a
to get to where as plausibility which is
so important to the practice of Sciences
you know having a sense of we should
take this seriously we should take this
seriously which that doesn't mean the
scientist says that that's the truth
I've concluded but the scientists is no
no we should take this seriously a deep
part of serious play is what things do
you do what habits like to use Aristotle
what virtues do you cultivate so that
you regularly and reliably show up and
take seriously what the other person is
saying right and so that you and and
then you can also you know encourage
them and in care them to take you
seriously as well well John you you
embody this and show up with that you
know with that disposition in such a
beautiful way and I'm deeply
appreciative of of it both personally
and also as someone who cares about how
we are making the world together all of
us and the moment at that the moment you
know I appreciate I really appreciate
how you're showing up and look I died I
feel I feel as though bringing this
dialogue to a closure now is his right
and so you know thank you so much
I I look forward to I look forward to
further further dialogues in the future
yeah well you you could tell how how
excited I was when I saw you showing up
that happy to see you and I'm happy to
interact with you I think you too I
think you bring I think you bring a
tremendous depth and flexibility and
finesse to how you show up and how you
engage and how you participate in these
dialogues and and you also are so
articulate are I I would really love to
see you talk with Christopher Mouser
Pietro my dear friend because his innate
capacity or
that's both innate and I think Heidi
train his innate capacity for mmm
lyrical expression and insightful
articulation I think the two of you
would just vibrate off against each
other and just a powerful and profound
way so I encourage you to speak with him
but I I think what you bring to this
makes it deeply enjoyable in that not so
much pleasure but I experience deep joy
and in this time we've shared together
so thank you very very much for it I
really appreciate it